This is the Big Thunder Mountain
Railroad,
a mine train roller coaster rattling
down the tracks at 45 kmh.
One guest will not make it through this
next ride alive.
Disneyland calls itself the happiest
place on earth.
>> This kingdom of fantasy and imagination
is the happiest place on earth.
>> Life-sized movie characters, blissful
kids, and carefree parents. Safety on
the rides is supposed to be the park's
top priority. But something has changed
over the past few years. During the Big
Thunder Mountain Railroad crash, riders
suffer broken ribs, facial cuts, and
painful chest injuries. One person dies.
And this is not the only fatal accident
in the park.
How did this happen? How did the
happiest place on earth turn into a
nightmare? At the turn of the
millennium, we talked to journalists,
engineers, and writers to piece the
story together. It seemed like every
couple of weeks there was some new
headline of some horrible thing that
happened at Disneyland. He warned them
in writing several times and they
ignored him. They ignored him because it
didn't fit into their proposal.
>> As it turns out, these accidents were no
unfortunate coincidence. They appear to
have been the result of calculated
corporate cost cutting and disastrous
negligence by the staff. And at the
center of it all sits one of the world's
most powerful consulting firms,
McKenzie.
Confirm.
My first time I visited Disneyland was
in the summer of 1969.
Uh I was uh 6 years old. I just remember
the feeling of being someplace unlike
any place I'd visited ever before in my
life. It was it was truly a magical
feeling. For many, a trip to Disneyland,
California is a lifelong dream,
something they travel from all over the
world to experience. Walt Disney, the
legendary founder of the Entertainment
Empire, once said, "I don't want the
public to see the world they live in
while they're in Disneyland. I want them
to feel they're in another world."
Disneyland is just able to tap into
something that no place else has.
combination of joy, nostalgia,
innocence,
color, light, music, all with a a story
personalized for each person uh playing
in the background that sews it all
together through familiar images and
characters. This is David Koik. He's
written several books about Disneyland,
and over the years, he has interviewed
around a thousand Disney employees.
Disneyland California opened in 1955,
and for decades, it was considered one
of the safest theme parks in the world.
In 1991, an expert magazine even
recognized the park's facilities
division as the world's best maintenance
organization. But at some point, others
start calling the shots.
This is Paul Pressler. He's been
Disneyland California's top executive
for 3 years now. On paper, the numbers
don't look bad. The parks division is
turning a healthy profit. But Presler is
determined to squeeze out more because
Disney stocks aren't doing so well.
>> He wanted to impress the board and the
way you do that is by cutting expenses.
It's the quickest way and the way to do
that was by cutting maintenance.
>> That's Walt Bogdanic, a New York Times
journalist. We interviewed him and his
colleague Mike Foresight for this video.
They co-authored this book, a key source
for our research. You'll find the link
in the description.
Presler is a former toy industry
executive and known as a hard-nosed cost
cutter. And for that, he brought in help
from McKenzie. McKenzie is one of the
most prestigious consulting firms in the
world. The company hires only the best
of the best. Clients pay up to $1,200
per hour for their expertise. Now, a few
of those consultants have drawn up a
plan to make Disneyland even more
profitable. And today, they're pitching
their ideas to Prestler.
They spent over a year studying every
facet of Disneyland looking for ways to
cut costs.
>> Initially, uh, McKenzie and company came
in and targeted the maintenance division
that was known as one of the most
respected facilities divisions of any
company anywhere. And yet, the
consultants aimed to slash the
division's budget by 25%. Mainly by
cutting staff.
To do that, they borrowed a concept from
the aviation industry called reliability
centered maintenance or RCM. The idea is
that maintenance decisions should not be
based on the intuition of experienced
employees, but on the analysis of repair
histories and breakdown rates. According
to McKenzie, the resulting increase in
efficiency would allow the park to let
go or transfer about half of its
maintenance staff, and that would save
Disney up to $16.9 million per year.
Presler goes on to put many of those
recommendations into practice.
In the past, maintenance workers were
each assigned to one specific ride,
which they ended up knowing inside out.
Now, they're floated between several
attractions to maximize efficiency.
Also, most maintenance workers are
transferred to the night shift. Only a
small emergency response team remains to
handle mechanical breakdowns during the
day. That way, the mechanics can work
undisturbed after the park closes its
gates. Moving more folks to third shift
probably made some sense, but not moving
almost everyone because there are many
things that can't be done in the middle
of the night when it's dark and cold and
wet. You're not going to effectively
painting a building in the middle of the
night. Many employees complain it's a
harsh change for people who've worked
days almost their entire lives. Many of
them were devastated by these changes.
To suddenly have your working conditions
worsened by tenfold. You know, if you're
working suddenly graveyard shift and
never able to see your family, being
exhausted on your job, being rushed
through what you had to do. McKenzie
responds by granting all overnight
workers a free annual subscription to
the Working Knights newsletter. It
features leading experts sharing shift
work wisdom on nutrition, sleep, and a
healthy family work balance. To no
avail, according to David Koig, more and
more employees are soon being treated
for high blood pressure and other stress
related symptoms. Night work
significantly increases the risk of
chronic health issues and is simply not
very healthy. So, management brings in
psychological counselors. They advise
insightful suggestions such as to use
caffeine to stay alert and have their
loved ones videotape daytime family
activities so the workers can stay
connected to them.
Robert Clrike is part of Disneyland's
maintenance crew. One day he's
interviewed by a McKenzie consultant to
review his routine on the Big Thunder
Mountain Railroad. The consultant asks
him, "Why do you inspect the lap bars
every single day? Those are the
restraints that hold passengers in their
seats." And according to Mackenzie's
data, they have never failed.
>> And the maintenance workers said, "Well,
the reason there's no accidents is
because we check the lap bars every
day." And it was almost as if, you know,
we're not going to do if we were an
airline, we're not going to do
pre-flight checks because we haven't had
accidents in a while. In 1997, Close
Strike sent an internal memo to warn his
supervisors. the ongoing staff shortage
and labor distribution could no longer
guarantee effective daily preventative
management.
>> He warned them in writing several times
and they ignored him. Um they ignored
him because it didn't fit into their
proposal which was look cost cutting if
we do it in a rational way is a good
thing.
There are better ways to make an
organization more efficient. UDU is an
all-in-one business management software
that replaces countless scatter tools
with one seamlessly integrated platform.
It offers over 45 apps from project
management and HR to accounting,
website, sales, and much more. It's all
in there. One of the easiest apps to
start with is invoicing. UDU's invoicing
app let you create and send invoices in
seconds. Pick the customer, add your
product or service, set quantities,
price, billing terms, and email it off
instantly. A dedicated portal lets
customers pay using their preferred
method. Payments are easy to track by
synchronizing your bank account. UDU
also supports PPE for B2B electronic
invoicing, helping businesses stay
compliant with upcoming European
regulations. Your first UDU app is free
for life with unlimited hosting and
support. And starting at 1990 per month,
you can unlock the full UDU suite as
your business grows. Check out the link
in the description to get started. Back
in 1997, Cluster Strike is concerned
that the new system can no longer
guarantee proper maintenance. And
unfortunately, time will prove him
right.
But who exactly are these consultants
and how do they work?
This is Eric Edstrom. He holds an MBA
and a master's degree in environmental
science from Oxford. Edstrom has served
as a soldier in Afghanistan. He returned
disillusioned and is now determined to
make a difference. He wants to help
fight climate change. McKenzie promises
him exactly that. Dream with me for a
second. What if we could be the largest
private sector catalyst for
decarbonization in the world?
>> To change the world, make the world just
a little bit better place.
>> To bring a new future to life, doing
something that's meaningful to our
clients and ultimately the societies
they act on and being an enabler for
that kind of change. That is change that
matters.
In 2018, after working for another
consulting group, Edstrom joins
McKenzie, he's full of energy and
optimism. If there's one thing McKenzie
does very, very well, it's recruit the
best and brightest
from elite universities uh in Europe and
the United States and in Asia as well.
They appeal to young people, really
bright people, you know, with a very
attractive package that you'll be able
to learn about uh business in the world,
and you might also make a positive
difference in the world. It's about
money.
>> McKenzie is one of the most coveted
employers on the planet. Each year,
nearly a million people apply for just a
few thousand spots. Only about 1% make
it in. The firm claims to serve 90 of
the top 100 corporations worldwide.
McKenzie also advises governments around
the world from ICE in the US and the
German Defense Ministry to past stints
with Saudi Arabia and Russia.
>> They're doctors for companies. They're
corporate doctors. That's how they like
to view themselves. In the most simple
terms, they have knowledge that for many
reasons companies pay for and they pass
on that knowledge for good or ill uh to
their clients.
Hiring McKenzie means getting support
from a small army of exceptionally smart
and highly trained advisers. These
consultants help managers with some of
their most challenging tasks acquire
other companies, drive innovation, or
cut costs. Or at least they try to help.
One of the problems is that when you
hire McKenzie, you're hiring young
people who don't have experience. You're
hiring people who don't know your
industry and you're paying them a lot of
money because supposedly they have this
genius because they're McKenzie. They
know what to do, but often they don't
know what to do and frankly they're just
doing what management tells them to do
because management doesn't want to take
responsibility for layoffs or for cost
cutting. So, it's easier to say, "Hey,
well, McKenzie told us to do it."
>> Disneyland chairman Paul Presler and
McKenzie go on to form a highly
profitable alliance. The consultants
deliver good numbers which appear to
legitimize the layoffs and budget cuts.
Meanwhile, Presley continues to climb
the ranks inside Disney.
The effects of the rigid cost cutting
slowly start to show throughout the
park. Paint is peeling here and there.
Rides break down more often. And when
the lights on Main Street go dark, no
one replaces the bulbs anymore.
>> Most of that preventive maintenance was
gone. And it was just sort of emergency
lastm minute slap dash get this thing
working in the middle of the night
maintenance. Uh things were breaking
down constantly. The late '9s you would
walk through Disneyland and it would be
a third of the attractions could be
closed. Unfortunately um there were
consequences for these many decisions of
moving to people in charge who didn't
necessarily have a familiarity with how
to operate the attractions.
Christmas Eve 1998. Lann Dawson is 33
and works as a software engineer at
Microsoft. He and his wife and son are
standing in line for a ride called
Rivers of America. The Colombia, an
old-fashioned river boat, is approaching
the dock.
According to David Koig, management
significantly reduced the number of crew
members to the bare minimum of three.
Today, one of them is running late.
Another colleague agrees to fill in at
the last minute. She's standing at the
dock holding a nylon rope and ready to
dock the ship. Disneyland's safety
protocol says she should wait until the
Columbia has fully stopped and reversed,
but she's new to the section of the
park. 2 months ago, she completed a
10-day crash course covering seven
different attractions. She has never
docked the Columbia before and has not
been trained to operate the ride. The 4
kg iron cleat on the ship's hole is
loose. The wood around it is rotten. She
throws the rope too early. The ship is
still moving
and the cleat is torn from the ship.
It shoots back towards the dock and hits
the employees foot and ankle.
Then it ricochets upwards, crushing
Luendos's school and striking his wife
across the face.
The dock is almost immediately cleaned
by Disneyland personnel. According to
Koig, they also brief witnesses on what
to say to the police, but officers don't
arrive for 5 hours. Apparently, they
only heard about the accident from the
paramedics. 48 hours later, Luan Dawson
is declared brain dead at the hospital
and taken off his respirator.
An investigation by the competent
authority blames the accident on
inadequate staff training. Several
employees will later remember having
noticed the loose cleat and the rotting
wood around it, but it was obviously
never repaired. The weak wood is never
formally identified as a cause of the
accident. The new regime and the
McKenzie recommendations had made so
many cutbacks. Everything sort of
accumulated into this perfect storm of
terror. It was horrible. The Dawson
family sues the park for damages. Disney
settles out of court and pays an
estimated 20 to $25 million. The exact
terms of the settlement are sealed. At
first, Disneyland reacts by updating
ride procedures and bringing back
experienced ride operators across the
park. But according to David Koig, many
of these safety measures are quietly
rolled back soon after. some new
procedures were instituted immediately
um as far as uh extra precautions in how
to operate the ship. But unfortunately,
many of the most important reasons that
allowed this accident to happen related
to the cutbacks, those were allowed to
continue. It was forgotten because it
was believed that McKenzie was doing the
right thing and Disney was doing the
right thing by listening to them. And
accidents do happen. I mean that is a
fact. There's no way that you know a
company can avoid all all problems. What
they really tried to do at least try to
interpret their actions from the outside
appear to be doing was to protect their
own bad decisions and cutbacks as to
sort of cover their backsides.
>> 2 months after the Columbia tragedy,
maintenance worker Robert Clustrike
resends his warning. This time he
submits it directly to one of the park's
senior managers. He writes, "I'm
concerned that the attractions are
deteriorating even more." Shortly after,
Clustrike is fired. Disney claims he was
let go because he refused to work night
shifts. Claustri himself believes he was
dismissed for blowing the whistle. The
cost cutting doesn't seem to slow down
Paul Presler's own ascent. By the time
of the Columbia accident, he had just
been promoted to president of the entire
Disney theme park division. But this is
only the beginning.
In 2000, a 4-year-old boy named Brandon
Zucker falls out of a spinning car on
the Roger Rabbit cartoon spin. He's
trapped under the following car and
stuck there for 10 minutes before first
responders can get him out. Brandon
suffers severe brain damage and can
never walk or talk again. He dies at
just 13 years old.
There's no evidence that ties the
accident directly to the cost cutting
measures, but an official investigation
once again cites grave mistakes
committed by the staff. Brandon Zucker
should never have been seated closest to
the cutout entryway of the car. Also,
ride operators probably failed to
properly lower his lap bar. It stands to
reason that better training might have
prevented the tragedy from happening. To
my knowledge, the experts from McKenzie
Company that were brought in, none of
them had any theme park experience. They
were all folks who were trained in doing
business better in general. In a sense,
that's what Disney really wanted. Their
company had been run by theme park
experts since its founding 40 years
before. McKenzie is hired to solve
problems and make companies better. But
better in what way? Better for whom?
McKenzie has made a lot of money working
for the tobacco industry. It has advised
authoritarian governments and has helped
the ICE department in the US quote
unquote optimize its detention and
deportation processes. But perhaps the
most haunting example is this one. Since
the mid90s, US pharmaceutical company
Purdue has been selling a drug called
Oxycottton. The company said it had a
low risk of addiction, but that claim
turned out to be false. As of 2004,
McKenzie was deeply involved in helping
produce turbocharged sales of the highly
addictive opioid. One strategy involved
identifying which doctors were most
likely to generate the biggest increases
in oxycottton prescriptions if actively
targeted by Purdue's sales force. We
know all this because McKenzie admitted
to it in court. McKenzie also helped
Purdue avoid problems with the US Food
and Drug Administration. The FDA also
happened to be one of Mackenzie's
clients.
You know, not only was McKenzie working
with the regulator and then the
industries, but also sometimes it was
the same consultants doing that work.
The same consultants would be advising
the Food and Drug Administration in the
United States, and they would also be on
a project with an opioid maker.
>> Since 1999, more than 850,000 people in
the US have died from opioid related
overdoses. Purdue isn't the only
culprit, but the company played a major
role in fueling America's opioid crisis.
Eventually, thousands of opioid lawsuits
were filed against Purdue Pharma and its
owners, the Sackler family. They agreed
to a $7.4 billion settlement after
previously paying $5.5 billion in fines.
The company is now bankrupt. McKenzie
spent years shaping Purdue strategy.
Walkbanage says they've always used the
same exact excuse to dodge any sort of
responsibility. They can always say and
have said that we just gave advice, we
didn't give orders. They can always slip
out of responsibility by saying that
well we recommended it but we didn't
carry out the orders. And that worked
for a long time until the opioid crisis.
We were able to look at thousands and
thousands of documents about that case
and it really did present a picture of
these McKenzie consultants that were
working extremely close with the
management. They were part of the team
and the result was that they did have to
pay a price.
>> In 2024, McKenzie paid over $600 million
to settle investigations into its role
in the opioid crisis. The Firm since
apologized for its involvement. The
statement can still be found on its
official website. It reads, "This
terrible public health crisis and our
past work for opioid manufacturers will
always be a source of profound regret
for our firm." The statement also
emphasizes that the company introduced
comprehensive compliance reforms. And
yet, McKenzie even advised Purdue Pharma
on how to counter emotional messages
from families who lost members to opioid
overdoses. The firm also admitted to
this in court.
We don't know if Mackenzie offered a
similar service to Disney after. Well,
by now more and more Disneyland
employees are speaking up against
McKenzie.
But hey, doesn't every business try to
optimize?
And what's the big deal with making the
park more efficient?
Sure,
you can't please everyone during a
transition like this,
and McKenzie only ever gives advice. The
final shots are always called by the
park's management.
Marcelo Torres dies at only 22 years
old. His best friend was seated next to
him and survives severely injured. Nine
other passengers are hurt in the
accident.
That morning, staff at Big Thunder
Mountain Railroad had noticed a strange
noise coming from the train, but they
didn't know how to respond and ended up
hesitating too long.
Taurus's family sues Disney and
investigators step in. They conclude the
accident was the result of poor
maintenance and insufficient staff
training. But the family's lawyer goes
further. This was not just one mechanic
making a mistake. This was really
systemic to how they were running the
park.
There's still a lot we simply don't know
about the Disneyland case, like which
consultants were involved, which of
their recommendations were actually
implemented. Neither Disney nor Paul
Presler responded to our questions.
McKenzie denies any responsibility for
the accidents.
One of the biggest mysteries is the
maintenance system known as RCM, the
method the consultants borrowed from
other industries. RCM is considered a
gold standard in aviation, nuclear
industries, and railroad infrastructure.
So why didn't it work at Disneyland?
>> Sometimes that might be done as we would
say you know in English in cookie cutter
fashion and you know the same solution
for for different industries. Uh and so
you know perhaps what went wrong is they
tried this cookie cutter approach uh to
Disneyland that might have worked for
another industry but it it it didn't
work uh there.
>> Disney is not a normal factory. It's not
an assembly line where you can just take
things from other industries and say,
"Oh, well, what worked there in this
produce factory is going to work in
operating the Indiana Jones Adventure."
We reached out to Marius Bassin, one of
the leading experts on reliability
centered maintenance. His company,
Aladdon, owns the trademarks for two
major RCM protocols. Basson doesn't know
all the technical details of what
happened at Disneyland, but he strongly
doubts that RCM was applied correctly.
He thinks that in theory RCM could work
in a theme park environment. But he also
writes if RCM is used to reduce costs,
it is probably applied incorrectly. RCM
or reliability centered maintenance is
not cost- centered maintenance. The
problem with most RCM program
implementations is that senior
management and stockholders want to see
immediate benefits and cost reduction.
We don't know if RCM was applied
incorrectly at Disneyland or it's just
used as a pretext for cutting costs or
whether it was the wrong approach to
begin with. What we do know is that many
people believe the cost cutting measures
recommended by McKenzie have played a
role in the accidents. But was the firm
ever held accountable?
Eric Edstrom joined Mackenzie full of
hope and idealism, but he soon realizes
that the company was not living up to
its promises. I joined McKenzie in 2018
and while I was there I found that the
projects that were available were not
anything like what were advertised and
rather than what you might see on a
McKenzie website which talks about
vaccine cold storage or renewable energy
that in practice is far and few in
between. He grows increasingly
disillusioned. He can only watch as
McKenzie helps fossil fuel companies
become even more efficient at extracting
coal and oil from the ground. Even
though the firm had originally recruited
him with the prospect of fighting
climate change, eventually he's had
enough. He sends out a farewell
statement that ricochets around
Mackenzie offices across the globe. We
know it from the book when McKenzie
comes to town. As an organization,
McKenzie seems to talk a lot about
values and principles without taking a
valued or principled stand for much of
anything. In my mind, McKenzie is an
amoral institution, an organization that
regularly takes on clients who bring
harm to others.
We would have loved to hear Disney and
Paul Presler's take on the allegations
made against them. Unfortunately,
neither responded. We also sent a
laundry list of questions to McKenzie.
For example, we were curious about what
the consultants themselves thought about
their work at Disneyland. But instead of
giving concrete answers, McKenzie
pointed us to a general statement of
theirs from 2022. There it says that the
book by Walt Buckdanic and Mike
Foresight fundamentally misrepresents
the firm and its work. The statement
also claims that Mackenzie's clients
contributed to 80% of global CO2
reductions in recent years. We can't
independently verify that number, nor
whether Mackenzie's work for those
clients has anything to do with climate
mitigation. The allegation that
Mackenzie's work has directly
contributed to mass layoffs is rejected
as a stereotype about consultants. The
statement says that McKenzie is
typically hired to help clients grow
their business and expand their
workforce. The company has supposedly
learned from its mistakes and invested
around $1 billion in a new risk
management and compliance system. The
firm claims it now has the industry's
most rigorous client selection policy.
The statement further denies any form of
responsibility for the incidents at
Disneyland. So, we decided to follow up
again, asking what McKenzie had to say
about the many reports, suggesting the
firm's recommendations did play a role.
A spokesman replied, "We aren't
commenting on whether or not we served a
particular client, but rather we reject
the author's attempt to connect our work
to events and issues that we simply had
nothing to do with."
The firm was never sued over its
connection to Disneyland tragedies. Paul
Presley left Disney in 2002 and became
CEO of the Gap clothing chain. He is
currently the chairman of the board of
directors of eBay.
The family of Marcela Torres has reached
an outofc court settlement with Disney
for an undisclosed sum. The company
accepts responsibility for the Big
Thunder Mountain accident. Torres's
parents have given $500,000 from the
settlement to provide scholarships to
aspiring talents at their son's former
college.
Marcela Torres was a graphic artist.
So, there was just all this bad
publicity and we were about less than 2
years away from the 50th anniversary of
Disneyland. This is 2003
and the 50th anniversary of Disneyland
was planned to be the biggest
celebration the Disney company in any
facet has has ever had. They knew that
all cameras that not all attention,
everything would be on Disneyland.
Accidents were still relatively
infrequent, just much more frequent than
they they had been before. But when the
Big Thunder Mountain accident happened,
they realized, "Oh my gosh, what are we
doing? This has this has got to stop.
>> Oh my god, Chloe, we're going to
Disneyland.
Oh my god."
>> Disneyland eventually recovered. Since
2003, no visitors have died due to poor
maintenance or errors committed by the
staff. Apparently, with Mackenzie and
Presler gone, a shift in mentality
followed. the park returned to its one
stellar and globally renowned safety
standards.
>> And so that come 2005 for that 50th
anniversary, Disneyland was truly the
happiest place on earth once again.
>> In 2022, Disney once again hired
McKenzie. This time, the consultants
were asked to identify redundancies and
cost-saving opportunities across
Disney's operations. According to the
Wall Street Journal, McKenzie proposed
stripping top creative executives of
control over how their work is marketed.
And once again, Disney employees started
to protest against Mackenzie's
recommendations.